Guide to the Hendrik Willem van Loon papers, 1884-1972.
Van Loon, Hendrick Willem papers,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Hendrik Willem van Loon Papers, 1884-1972.
3292
Hendrik Willem, Van Loon 1882-1944.
36.1 cubic ft.
Correspondence, manuscripts, publications, journal clippings, illustrations, and photographs
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection consists of correspondence with family, friends, literary and other public figures, pertaining to his career as an author and his varied humanitarian concerns; much of the correspondence between 1939 and 1942 deals with refugees from Nazi persecution and van Loon's participation in war relief fund raising and committees.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Hendrik Willem van Loon was born in Rotterdam, Holland on January 14, 1882. He attended Cornell University, graduating in 1905. In 1906 he married Eliza Ingersoll Bowditch and began working for the Associated Press in New York City, Washington, D.C., Moscow, and Warsaw. His son Henry Bowditch van Loon was born on June 22, 1907, and Gerard Willem van Loon on January 16, 1911. Hendrik van Loon received his Ph.D. from the University of Munich in 1911, and in 1913 his book THE FALL OF THE DUTCH REPUBLIC was published. He lectured at Cornell on European History from 1915-1916. He married Helen Criswell ("Jimmie") in 1920 and in 1921 received the Newbery Medal for THE STORY OF MANKIND. From 1922-23 he was a professor at Antioch College, Ohio, and was Associate Editor of the BALTIMORE SUN from 1923-24. He did his first radio broadcast on Christmas Day, 1929, and started radio broadcasts at NBC in 1932. He did lectures for the Cunard Cruise Line on the FRANCONIA in 1934. In 1939-40 his radio broadcasts were directed to Holland from WRVL in Boston. He died in Old Greenwich, Connecticut on March 11, 1944.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection consists of correspondence with family, friends, literary and other public figures, pertaining to his career as an author and his varied humanitarian concerns; much of the correspondence between 1939 and 1942 deals with refugees from Nazi persecution and van Loon's participation in war relief fund raising and committees.
Also included are condolence letters received after Hendrik's death. A substantial portion of the papers are comprised of manuscripts for many of his books and their illustrative materials in pen-and-ink, pencil, and watercolors. There are many sketchbooks and miscellaneous sketches as well as those for the publications. Other documents include a manuscript of his Ph.D. in German, notes for a history course taught at Cornell, manuscripts for radio broadcasts (1935-42), articles by and about van Loon,including a recollection by John L. De Forest; phonograph records, photographs, picture puzzles, foreign language editions of his books, reviews, menus, the Newberry Medal which was presented to him at the meeting of The American Library Association in 1921, an unfinished portrait by the painter Leon Gordon, his and Helen Criswell van Loon's ("Jimmie's") passports, and pamphlets from the Cunard Cruise Ship FRANCONIA. Documenting his activities in literary circles in New York City are copies of MAD HATTER MUTTERINGS, 1920-21, which were satirical journals circulated in the Greenwich Village coffee shop where "Jimmie" worked and later became the owner; also included are her diaries, 1920-54; and Gerard Willem van Loon's correspondence and draft copies for his book about Hendrik. Includes a film and a video. Correspondents include Franklin and Eleanor Roosevelt, George Lincoln Burr, and others.
Also, "Histoire fameuse du sieur Jean Nepomuc Pantagruel, und von der hochlobigen Jungfrau Kunigunde," a fanciful manuscript story written and illustrated by Van Loon on a series of 93 postcards which he sent to the Misses Jones in Cambridge, Massachusetts over a period of months in 1912 (shelved as Bd. Ms. 1).
Letters from van Loon in America to the Netherlands commenting on the general atmosphere in wartime America (box 74).
Twenty-one drawings from late 1930's and 1940's.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Van Loon, Hendrik Willem, 1882-1944.; Bowditch, Eliza Ingersoll.; Burr, George Lincoln, 1857-1938.; De Forest, John L.(John Le Roy), 1916-; Gordon, Leon.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1963.; Roosevelt, Franklin D.(Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Van Loon, Gerard Willem.; Van Loon, Helen Criswell.; Van Loon, Hendrick Willem, 1882-1944.; Van Loon, Hendrick Willem, 1882-1944. Histoire fameuse du sieur Jean Nepomuc Pantagruel.; Van Loon, Henry Bowditch.; Antioch College.; Associated Press.; Cornell University.; Cunard Steamship Company, Ltd.; Franconia (Ship); Mad Hatter (Greenwich Village, New York, N.Y.); WRVL (Radio station, Boston, Mass.)
Titles:
Baltimore sun.; Mad hatter mutterings.
Subjects:
History--Study and teaching.; Radio broadcasting.; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief.; Authors.; Illustrators.; Journalists.
Places:
Germany.; Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.); Netherlands.; New York (N.Y.)
Form and Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Drawings.; Passports.; Photographs.; Sketchbooks.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. General correspondence
Boxes: 1-3
Subseries Ia. A chronological arrangement of general correspondence
Subseries Ib. Correspondence of a particular topic arranged chronologically
Series II. Family correspondence
Boxes: 4-17, F.10
Family correspondence of ten or more letters arranged chronologically. Family members include Hendrik's immediate family of parents, aunts, uncles, and two sons, and Eliza Bowditch van Loon's parents, her siblings, and cousins. Also postcards to and from family members. Major correspondence of ten or more letters between those friends with whom Hendrik maintained a regular correspondence is included in this series. Also included is correspondence between his second wife, Helen Criswell van Loon, and his third wife, Frances Ames Goodrich. This material is listed alphabetically by correspondent and arranged chronologically.
Series III. Major correspondents
Boxes: 17, F. 11-19
Major correspondents include those individuals who were considered important personalities in the 1900's-1940's, with whom Hendrik wrote irregularly (less than ten letters). This material is listed alphabetically and includes number of letters and inclusive dates. Also included in this series are draft copies of correspondence and microfilmed correspondence.
Series IV. Manuscript material
Boxes: 20-26
Manuscript material includes carbons, drafts, and typescripts for articles, books, broadcasts, lectures, serials, and Hendrik Willem van Loon's thesis. Book material is arranged alphabetically by title. Articles, broadcasts, lectures, serials, and the thesis are arranged separately in chronological order when possible. The letters N/A were used when no title was available.
Series V. Printed material
Boxes: 27-34
Printed material consists mainly of English and foreign translations of various van Loon books: articles about van Loon in both foreign and American papers and magazines; reviews; promotional book material; cruise ship pamphlets; copies of illustrations that appeared in various newspapers and magazines; and miscellaneous clippings.
Series VI. Illustrative material
Boxes: 35-52
Illustrative material includes the illustrations made for many van Loon books arranged by book title; sketches for unfinished books; sketchbooks; illustrated stories and unpublished material; illustrated folders, envelopes, and menus; small pen-and-ink and watercolor sketches either mounted or on mats; ornate matted sketches; book jackets; many miscellaneous sketches; and portraits of van Loon by other artists.
Series VII. Memorabilia
Boxes: 53-62 Map Case Special locations
Subseries VIIa. Includes scrapbooks, guestbooks, photograph albums and photographs, notebooks, diaries, passports, pamphlets, certificates, diplomas, phonograph records, games, puzzles, and miscellaneous.subseries
Subseries VIIb. Collected memorabilia includes various miscellaneous documents, volumes, and reprints collected by van Loon.
Series VIII. Papers of Helen Criswell "Jimmie" van Loon
Boxes: 63-64
Papers of Helen Criswell "Jimmie" van Loon include an original play, diaries, "Mad Hatter Mutterings," and other miscellaneous material.
Series IX. Papers of Gerard Willem van Loon
Boxes: 65-67
Papers of Gerard Willem van Loon includes drafts and photos for his biography about Hendrik Willem van Loon, and correspondence pertaining to his father and the manuscript.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series 1. General correspondence
  General correspondence is divided into two subseries: Subseries 1. A chronological arrangement of general correspondence. Subseries 2. Correspondence of a particular topic arranged chronologically.
  - Subseries Ia. General Correspondence Arranged Chronologically
    - 1902-1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1915 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1918, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1926-1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1930 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1936 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      -contains an envelope with a painting of a sailboat
    - 1937 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1939 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      -contains 3 photos of Van Loon, including one of him drawing (close-up of hands) and 2 of him standing next to an NBC microphone
    - 1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1942 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Jan. 1943-Mar. 1943 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Apr. 1943-May 1943 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - June 1943-Dec. 1943 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1944, and undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Subseries Ib. Correspondence of a particular topic arranged chronologically
    - Letters from Van Loon to the Netherlands commenting on wartime in America. Photocopies (Box 74)
    - Letters from reviewers about Hendrik Willem van Loon's Fall of the Dutch Republic, 1912-1914 (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
    - Letters of introduction, 1913-1916 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence pertaining to a job with the University of Wisconsin, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence to Mr. Zuberbuehler (about Willem's schooling), 1926-1929 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence concerning a debate that Verdi Alien was trying to set up that centered about Darwinian theories, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence about Queen Wilhelmina's knighting of Hendrik Willem van Loon, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Congratulation telegrams on Hendrik Willem van Loon's 60th Birthday (A-M, N-Z, Misc.) includes telegrams from H. Kerster and the Netherlands, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
    - Congratulation letters on Hendrik Willem van Loon's 60th Birthday (A-M, N-W, Misc.), 1942 (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
    - Correspondence about Van Loon's Lives, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
    - Correspondence about a pamphlet for the state of Connecticut, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence from World War II soldiers, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - War Relief correspondence, June 1941 - July 1941 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - War Relief correspondence, Aug. 1943-Jan. 1944 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Condolence telegrams (A-H, J-M, P-Z, Misc.), 1944 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - Condolence letters(A, B, C, D-E, F, G, H, J, K, L M, N-0, P, R, S, T,V, W-Z, Misc.), 1944 (Box 3, Folder 4-22)
    - Letters after Hendrik's death, 1944-1962 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Series II. Family correspondence
  Family correspondence of ten or more letters arranged chronologically.
  Family members include Hendrik's immediate family of parents, aunts, uncles, and two sons, and Eliza Bowditch van Loon's parents, her siblings, and cousins. Also postcards to and from family members. Major correspondence of ten or more letters between those friends with whom Hendrik maintained a regular correspondence is included in this series. Also included is correspondence between his second wife, Helen Criswell van Loon, and his third wife, Frances Ames Goodrich. This material is listed alphabetically by correspondent and arranged chronologically.
  - Subseries IIa. Chronologically Listed Letters
    - Early correspondence mostly in Dutch from Hendrik Willem van Loon's mother, father, and aunts and uncles, 1897-1899 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
    - Letters from Hendrik Willem van Loon to his mother in Dutch, c. 1900 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Early correspondence mostly in Dutch to and from Hendrik Willem van Loon's family, c. 1901-1904 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1905 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon's overseas letters, includes letter to Hendrik Willem van Loon from Eliza, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Jan. 1907 - May 1907 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous (including June 22-birth of Henry Bowditch), June 1907 - Aug. 1907 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Sept. 1907 - Dec. 1907 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - 1908 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - 1909 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - 1910 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Birth of Gerard Willem, Jan. 1911 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Feb. -Apr. 1911 (Box 4, Folder 15-16)
    - May 1911-[misc] (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - 1912 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - 1913 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - 1914 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - 1915 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - 1916 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - 1917 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Mar.1918 -July (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Aug.1918 - [misc] (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Jan. -July 1919 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Aug. 1919 - [misc] (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1920 Jan. 1920-July 1920 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Sept. 1920 - [misc] (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1921 Jan. 1921 -May 1921 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - June 1921 - [misc] (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - 1922 Jan. - May 1922 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - July 1922 - [misc] (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - 1923 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - 1924 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - 1925 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - 1926 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - 1927 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - 1928 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - 1929 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - 1930 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - 1931 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Jan. 1932 -Mar 1932 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Apr. 1932 - June 1932 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - July 1932 - Sept. 1932 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Oct. 1932 -[misc] (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Jan. 1933 - Mar. 1933 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Apr. 1933 - Aug. 1933 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Sept. 1933 - [misc] (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Jan. 1934 - May. 1934 (Box 6, Folder 8-10)
    - June. 1934 - Aug. 1934 (Box 6, Folder 8-10)
    - Sept. 1934 - [misc] (Box 6, Folder 8-10)
    - Jan. 1935 - Apr. 1935 (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
    - May 1935 - [misc] (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
    - 1936 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      Includes note to GWVL on back of a note to Hendrik Willem van Loon from Ed Sullivan, dated December 7, 1936
    - Jan. 1937 - Dec. 1937 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Jan. 1938 - June 1938 (Box 6, Folder 16-17)
    - July 1938 - [misc] (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - 1939 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Including letter from Henri Hanken
    - 1940 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 1941 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Jan. 1942 - Dec. 1942 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 5-9)
    - Letters to Gerard Willem 1943 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Jan. 1943 -May 1943 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - June 1943 - Dec. 1943 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 13-16)
    - 1944 (Box 7, Folder 17)
      Includes one letter to Henry Bowditch from Eliza after Hendrik Willem van Loon's death
  - Postcards
    - To: EBVL, 1888-1899 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1900-1903 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - 1904 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - 1905 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 1906 Jan. -June, July-Aug., Sept. -Oct., Nov. -misc., 1906 Jan. -June, July-Aug., Sept. -Oct., Nov. -misc. (Box 8, Folder 5-8)
    - 1907 Jan. -March, Apr. -June, July-Aug., Sept. -misc., 1907 Jan. -March, Apr. -June, July-Aug., Sept. -misc. (Box 8, Folder 9-12)
    - 1908 Jan. -Mar., Apr. -Sept., 1908 Jan. -Mar., Apr. -Sept. (Box 8, Folder 13-14)
    - 1908 Oct. -misc. includes postcards from Blok, 1908-1910, 1908 Oct. -misc. includes postcards from Blok, 1908-1910 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - 1909 Mar. -July, Aug. -misc., 1909 Mar. -July, Aug. -misc. (Box 8, Folder 16-17)
    - 1910 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - 1911 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - 1912 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - "Histoire fameuse du sieur Jean Nepomuc Pantagruel", 1912; Children's story written and illustrated by Van Loon and mailed to the Misses Jones on a series of 93 postcards. (Volume Bd. Ms. 1)
    - 1913 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - 1914 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - 1915 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - 1916 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - 1917-1920 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - 1921, 1923 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - 1924-1925, 1930, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Subseries IIc. Correspondence To And From Hendrik Willem van Loon
    - Helen Augur, 1931-1942 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Harold Bauer, 1931-1934 (to and from) 1935-1944 (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
    - William Berger, 1929 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1928 Feb., Mar., Apr., May (Box 9, Folder 5-8)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1928 June-Sept. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1928 Oct. -misc. (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1929 Jan. -May (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1929 June-Dec. (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1930 Jan. -June (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1930 July, Aug. (Box 9, Folder 14-15)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1930 Sept. -Nov. (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1931 Jan. -Apr. (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1931 May- Aug. (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1931 (undated) (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1932 Feb. -Oct. (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1932 (undated) (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1933 Jan, Apr. -Dec. (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1933 (undated) (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1934 Jan. -May (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1934 June-July (Box 9, Folder 25a)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1934 Aug. -Oct. (letter to Harvard about a "Jewish" scholarship) (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1937 (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1938 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1939 Feb. -Apr. (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1939 May-Dec., n.d. (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1940-1941 (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Alice Bernheim, 1942-1944 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Morris Bishop, 1914-1943 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Fraser Bond, 1941-1944, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Dr. Frank Boyden, 1923-1925, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Florence Brobeck, 1935-1941, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - George Lincoln Burr, 1902-1904 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - George Lincoln Burr, 1905-1907 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - George Lincoln Burr, 1908-1913 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - George Lincoln Burr, 1914-1917 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - George Lincoln Burr, 1918-1935 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Dr. H. Colijn, 1939-1940 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1887 (letter from Helen Criswell van Loon's father) (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1903 (letter from Bryn Mawr College) (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1919 Sept. (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1919 Oct. (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1919 Nov. 1-15 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1919 Nov. 16-24 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1919 Nov. 25, 1920 Jan. 5 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1926 Oct. -Dec. (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1927 Jan. -Feb. (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1927 Mar. -June (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1927 July- Aug. (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1927 Dec. (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1928 Sept. (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1929 March (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1929 Aug., ca. 1929 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1930 Jan., Mar. 2-6 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1930 Mar. 11-25 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1930 Mar. 26-29 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1930 April (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1930 June 6-July 16 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1930 Oct. 6-18, Nov. 8 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1933 June 19-July 11 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1933 Sept. -Nov. (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1934-1935 (includes legal correspondence about the estate of Mary-Ann Hostetter) (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1936 Apr. 18-30 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1936 May 1-4 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, 1945-1959 (includes bills from convalescent home, and obituary) (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Helen Criswell Van Loon, n. d. (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Elmer Davis, 1939-1943. (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Albert Einstein, 1930-1943, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Ruby Fuhr, 1929 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Ruby Fuhr, 1930 Jan. -Feb. (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Ruby Fuhr, 1930 Mar. -July (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Ruby Fuhr, 1930 Aug. -Dec. (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Ruby Fuhr, 1931 Feb. -Aug. (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Ruby Fuhr, 1931 Sept. -Dec. (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Ruby Fuhr, 1932 Jan. -May (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Ruby Fuhr, 1932 June-Dec. (Box 11, Folder 25)
    - Ruby Fuhr, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 26)
    - Ruby Fuhr, 1934 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Ruby Fuhr, 1935 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Ruby Fuhr, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Ruby Fuhr, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Ruby Fuhr, 1938 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Ruby Fuhr, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Ruby Fuhr, 1940-1941 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Ruby Fuhr, 1942, 1944 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Ruby Fuhr, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1925 July (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1925 Aug. 1-5 (with copy of chapter 32, The Last Hundred Years) (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1925 Aug. 6-10 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1925 Aug. 11-15 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1925 Aug. 16-19 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1925 Aug. 20-21 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1925 Aug. 22-25 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1925 Aug. 26-29 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1925 Aug. 30-31 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1925 Sept. 1-10 (includes small drawings) (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1925 Sept. 11-13 (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1925 Sept. 14-19 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1925 Sept. 20-24 (includes small drawings) (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1925 Sept. 25-30 (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1925 Oct. (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1925 Nov. -Dec. (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1925-1926 letters from F.G. (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1926 (from van Loon) (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1927 Jan. 5-19 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1927 Jan. 20-31 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1927 Feb. -Mar. (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1927 May- June (includes small drawings) (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1927 Oct.. -Dec. (includes letter to Hendrik from Frances, and small drawings) (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1927 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1927 letters (dated by Gerard W. van Loon collectively, June 6-July 27) (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Frances Goodrich, c. 1926 (includes letter from Frances) (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Frances Goodrich, 1928-1934 (Frances' letter to investigator) (Box 13, Folder 11)